Finding Aid for the Charles Lanman Papers LSC.0728
UCLA Library Special Collections
Charles Lanman papers
1840-1892
UCLA Library Special Collections
Lanman, Charles
LSC.0728
2.0 linear feet (4 boxes)
Charles Lanman (1819-1895) was an editor, librarian, and author. He also wrote travel accounts of his explorations in wilderness areas of the eastern United States, and is best known as the publisher of the Dictionary of Congress, first issued in 1859. The collection consists of holograph manuscripts of Lanman's published works, portions of two unpublished manuscript autobiographies, manuscripts of his works on travel in the U.S., and his biographical sketches.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Purchased from W.H. Lowdermilk, 1960.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9919730583606533
Biography
Lanman was born on June 14, 1819 in Monroe, Michigan; worked ten years at a business in New York City before returning to Michigan to edit the Monroe gazette in 1845; the next year was the associate editor of the Cincinnati chronicle, and in 1847 was an assistant on the New York express; in 1849 he became librarian of the War Department in Washington, D.C.; in 1850 he became librarian of copyrights and private secretary of Daniel Webster, and in 1853 examiner of depositories for the southern states; from 1855-57 he served as librarian and head of the returns office in the Interior Department, in 1866 the librarian of the House of Representatives, and from 1871-82, secretary to the Japanese legation; wrote travel accounts of his explorations of wilderness areas of the eastern United States; best known as the publisher of the Dictionary of Congress, first issued in 1859; he died in 1895.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of holograph manuscripts of Charles Lanman's published works, all with revisions for editions that were never published. Also includes portions of two unpublished manuscript autobiographies. Contains manuscripts of his works on travel in the U.S. and his biographical sketches.
Expanded Scope and Content
The letters, papers and manuscripts of Charles Lanman (1819-1895) are scattered in a number of repositories throughout the United States. This small collection of Lanman's writings was purchased in 1960 from W.H. Lowdermilk & Company, booksellers, Washington, D.C., with the assistance of Dr. E. Maurice Bloch of the Department of Art, UCLA.
Lowdermilk & Company purchased the Charles Lanman Library, and apparently this collection of manuscripts was among the books in the library. The library has long since been dispersed, however, the manuscripts were retained and were discovered in 1960 by Dr. Bloch in the basement of Lowdermilk & Company, Washington, D.C.
The collection contains some of Lanman's published and unpublished works. Two Lanman letters, purchased by the Library in 1940, have been added to the collection. The following is a register with description of the items in the collection.
James V. Mink
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Eventide recollections, My ships of thought, or, A booklover's monologue (Box 1).
Haphazard personalities, Curious characters and pleasant places (Box 2). "Presidential recollections," "Recollections of Michigan," "Octavius Perinchief," "Letters from a motley crew," "Literary ladies," "An quixotic Yankee," "The old Connecticut Academy," "Narrow escaper," untitled manuscript (Box 3).
"Adventures of an angler in Canada," Letters from the Alleghany Mountains and the source of the Potomac, "A summer in the wilderness," "A tour to the River Restigouche," "A winter in the South," "From the River Potomac to Mount Desert," "In the evening twilight" (Box 4).
Correspondence (Boxes 3-4).
Travelers' writings, American.; Librarians -- United States -- Archives.; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives.; Manuscripts for publication; Lanman, Charles, 1819-1895--Archives.
- Autobiography and Reminiscences of Charles Lanman
  Scope and Contents note
  Contained in two manuscripts written in his later life and apparently unpublished: Eventide Recollections and My Ships of Thought; or a Booklover's Monologue.
  - Eventide Recollections. Washington, D.C., ca. 1890 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
    - "A family monologue" (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Lamaniana" [and Charles James Lanman]. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Recollections of New York." (Box 1, Folder 3)
      General note
      Missing, March 2003 (JF).
    - "Newspaper Recollections." (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Artistic Recollections." (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Literary Recollections." (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - My Ships of Thought; or a Booklover's Monologue. Washington, D.C., circa. 1892 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes recollections concerning the publication of his Dictionary of congress.
    A copy in Negative microfilm collection, no.04721.
- Manuscripts
  Containing biographies of various persons, chiefly Americans, with whom Lanman was acquainted. Many of these were written for newspapers and were later collected and published in his Haphazard Personalities; Chiefly of Noted Americans (Boston: Lee and Shephard; New York: C.T. Trillingham, 1886). Each biography is paginated separately; many are corrected drafts, with additions, of articles published at an earlier date.
  - Haphazard Personalities.... Washington, D.C., ca. 1885 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Curious Characters and Pleasant Places. Published: Edinburgh., 1881 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Presidential Recollections." Washington, D.C., ca. 1890 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Revisions, with additions, of a newspaper article published earlier.
    [Contains 2 letters from James A. Garfield, March 28, 1874 and January 24, 1871 and one from Chester A. Arthur, April 28, 1881]
  - "Recollections of Michigan." Washington, D.C. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Revisions, with a few additions, of an article published earlier.
  - Octavius Perinchief. Washington, D.C. [published]., 1879 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Letters from a Motley Crew." Washington, D.C., ca. 1889 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Published as part of his Riverside Essays[?].
  - "Literary Ladies." Washington, D.C. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Revision, with additions, of an earlier newspaper article.
  - "An Quixotic Yankee." Washington, D.C. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "The Old Connecticut Acadaemy." Washington, D.C. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Revision, with a few corrections, of an earlier work.
  - "Narrow Escapes." Washington, D.C. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Revision, with corrections and additions, of an earlier article.
  - [Untitled (first page missing) manuscript] Washington, D.C. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    [Recollections of Washington, D.C. in the post Civil War years.]
  - ["Adventures of an Angler in Canada,.. ."], [1848] (Box 4, Folder 1)
    A revision, with additions and corrections, of his earlier work on angling for inclusion in his Adventures in the Wilds of the United States and British American Provinces (Philadelphia: J.W. Moore, 1856).
  - "Letters from the Alleghany Mountains and the Sources of the Potomac." Washington, D.C., ca. 1856 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Revised draft, with additions and corrections, for inclusion in his Adventures in the Wilds of the United States..., 1856.
  - "A Summer in the Wilderness...." Washington, D.C., 1856 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Revised draft of an earlier work ("A Summer in the Wilderness; Embracing a Canoe Voyage on the Upper Mississippi and Lake Superior." New York: D. Appleton & Company; Philadelphia: G.S. Appleton, 1847) with additions and corrections for his Adventures in the Wilds of the United States..., 1856.
  - "A Tour to the River Restigouche." Washington, D.C. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Revision, with corrections and additions, of a section of his Adventures in the Wilds of the United States, 1856.
  - "A Winter in the South." Washington, D.C. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Revision, with corrections and additions, of a section of his Adventures in the Wilds of the United States..., 1856.
  - From the River Potomac to Mount Desert. Washington, D.C. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    A manuscript composed of earlier articles with corrections and additions [Unpublished?].
  - In the Evening Twilight., 1813 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Manuscript of some poems by Lanman[?].
  - Two letters from Charles Lanman., 1862 and 1875 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    To Benjamin Perley Poore (June 19, 1862).
    To John Neafie (February 20, 1875).
    The letter to Benjamin P. Poore contains a reference to President Abraham Lincoln and Charles Summer.
  - Letter to D. Appleton & Company. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Two letters to Lanman., 1867 and 1875 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    From Congressman R.P. Spalding (1867).
    From Congressman Scott Lord (1875).